In Africa we say,
في أفريقيا نحن نقول،
"God gave the white man a watch
" الله أعطى الرجل الأبيض ساعة
and gave the black man time."
وأعطى الرجل الأسود الزمن."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I think, how is it possible
أعتقد، كيف يمكن
for a man with so much time
لشخص لديه الكثير من الوقت
to tell his story in 18 minutes?
أن يحكي قصة حياته في ١٨ دقيقة.
I think it will be quite a challenge for me.
أعتقد أنه سيكون تحدياً كبيراً بالنسبة لي.
Most African stories these days,
معظم القصص الأفريقية في هذه الأيام،
they talk about famine,
تتحدث عن المجاعة،
HIV and AIDS,
فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة والإيدز،
poverty or war.
الفقر أو الحرب.
But my story that I would like to share with you today
لكن قصتي التي أريد مشاركتها معكم اليوم
is the one about success.
هي قصة عن نجاح.
It is about a country
إنها عن دولة
in the southwest of Africa
في جنوب غرب أفريقيا
called Namibia.
تسمى ناميبيا.
Namibia has got 2.1 million people,
عدد سكان نامبيبا هو ٢,١ مليون نسمة،
but it is only twice the size of California.
لكنها فقط ضعف مساحة كالفورنيا.
I come from a region
أنا من منطقة
in the remote northwest part of the country.
في أقصى الجزء الشمالي الغربي للبلاد.
It's called Kunene region.
إنها تسمى منطقة كنيوني.
And in the center of Kunene region
وفي منتصف منطقة كنيوني
is the village of Sesfontein. This is where I was born.
توجد قرية سيسفونتيان. هناك حيث وُلدت.
This is where I'm coming from.
ومن هنا جئت.
Most people that are following the story
معظم الناس الذين يتابعون قصة
of Angelina Jolie
أنجليانا جولي
and Brad Pitt
وبراد بت
will know where Namibia is.
سيعرفون أين هي ناميبيا.
They love Namibia
إنهم يحبون ناميبيا
for its beautiful dunes,
لكثبانها الرملية الجميلة،
that are even taller
التي هي أطول بكثير
than the Empire State Building.
من مبنى امباير ستيت.
Wind and time have twisted our landscape
الرياح والزمن قاما بتغيير مناظرنا الطبيعية
into very strange shapes,
إلى أشكال غريبة جدا.
and these shapes are speckled with wildlife
وهذه الأشكال منقَّطة بالحياة البرية
that has become so adapted
التي أصبحت تتكيف بشدة
to this harsh and strange land.
مع هذه الأرض القاسية والغريبة.
I'm a Himba.
أنا من قبيلة الهيمبا.
You might wonder, why are you wearing these Western clothes?
وربما تستغربون، لماذا نرتدي هذه الملابس الغربية؟
I'm a Himba and Namibian.
أنا من قبيلة الهيمبا وفي نفس الوقت ناميبي.
A Himba is one of the 29
وقبيلة الهيمبا هي أحد 29
ethnic groups in Namibia.
مجموعة عرقية في ناميبيا.
We live a very traditional lifestyle.
نحن نعيش حياة تقليدية للغاية.
I grew up herding,
لقد نشأت في الرعي،
looking after our livestock --
أرعى ماشيتنا --
goats, sheep and cattle.
الماعز، الخراف والماشية.
And one day,
وفي أحد الأيام،
my father actually took me into the bush.
أخذني والدي إلى الأدغال.
He said, "John,
وقال، " جون،
I want you to become a good herder.
أريدك أن تصبح راعي ماشية جيد.
Boy, if you are looking after our livestock
ولدي، إذا كنت ترعى ماشيتنا
and you see a cheetah
ورأيت فهداً
eating our goat --
يلتهم أغنامنا،
cheetah is very nervous --
والفهد في حالة هياج شديد.
just walk up to it.
فقط أمشي تجاهه.
Walk up to it and smack it on the backside."
أمشي تجاهه وأصفعه على مؤخرته."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"And he will let go of the goat
" وسيقوم بترك الغنم
and run off."
وسيهرب."
But then he said,
لكنه استطرد،
"Boy, if you run into a lion,
" ولدي، إذا واجهت الأسد ،
don't move.
لا تتحرك.
Don't move. Stand your ground.
لا تتحرك. قف مكانك.
Puff up and just look it in the eye
تنفس وأنظر له في عينيه
and it may not want to fight you."
فربما لا يريد أن يقاتلك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But then, he said,
لكنه استطرد،
"If you see a leopard,
" إذا رأيت نمر،
boy, you better run like hell."
ولدي، من الأفضل أن تركض بأسرع ما يمكن."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Imagine you run faster than those goats you are looking after."
"تخيل أنك تجري أسرع من تلك الأغنام التي تقوم برعايتها."
In this way --
بهذه الطريقة --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In this way, I actually started to learn about nature.
بهذه الطريقة، لقد بدأت في الواقع معرفة الطبيعة.
In addition to being an ordinary Namibian
كما تعلمون، بالإضافة لكوني ناميبي عادي
and in addition to being a Himba
وبالإضافة لكوني من قبيلة الهيمبا
I'm also a trained conservationist.
فأنا أيضاً متدرب على الحفاظ على البيئة.
And it is very important if you are in the field
ومن المهم جداً إذا كنت في ذلك المجال
to know what to confront
أن تعرف ما يجب عليك مواجهته
and what to run from.
وما يجب أن تجري منه.
I was born in 1971.
لقد وُلدت عام ١٩٧١.
We lived under apartheid regime.
وقد عشنا تحت دولة الفصل العنصري.
The whites could farm, graze
بمستطاع البيض أن يزرعوا، يرعوا
and hunt as they wished,
ويصيدوا كما يشاؤون،
but we black, we were not regarded as responsible
لكن نحن السود، لم نكن نعتبر أهلاً للثقة
to use wildlife.
لإستخدام الحياة البرية.
Whenever we tried to hunt,
كلما حاولنا الصيد،
we were called poachers.
كنا نُسَمَّى بالمنهكين.
And as a result, we were fined and locked up in jail.
ونتيجة لذلك، يتم تغريمنا ويلقى بنا في السجن.
Between 1966 and 1990,
بين عامي ١٩٦٦ و ١٩٩٠،
the U.S. and Soviet interests
مصالح الولايات المتحدة والإتحاد السوفيتي
fought for control over my country.
تقاطعت من أجل السيطرة على وطننا.
And you know, during war time,
وكما تعلمون، خلال فترة الحرب،
there are militaries, armies, that are moving around.
هناك مليشيات، جيوش، تحوم في الجوار.
And the army hunted for valuable rhino horns
وقد قام الجيش بالصيد من أجل قرون وحيد القرن القيمة
and tusks.
والأنياب.
They could sell these things for anything between
كانوا يبيعون هذه الأشياء مقابل أي شئ يتراوح بين
$5,000 a kilo.
ـ ٥,٠٠٠ دولار للكيلوغرام.
During the same year
خلال نفس السنة
almost every Himba had a rifle.
كان لكل فرد من الهيمبا تقريباً بندقية.
Because it was wartime,
لأنها كانت فترة الحرب،
the British .303 rifle
البندقية الإنجليزية ٣٠٣
was just all over the whole country.
كانت منتشرة في كل أرجاء البلاد.
Then in the same time, around 1980,
ثم في نفس الفترة، حوالي عام ١٩٨٠،
we had a very big drought.
شهدنا جفافاً كبيراً.
It killed almost everything that was left.
لقد قتل تقريباً كل ما تبقى.
Our livestock was
كانت ثروتنا الحيوانية
almost at the brink of extinction,
تقريباً على شفا الإنقراض،
protected as well.
و محمية أيضاً.
We were hungry.
كنا جوعى.
I remember a night
أذكر تلك الليلة
when a hungry leopard
عندما دخل نمر جائع
went into the house
إلى منزل
of one of our neighbors
أحد جيراننا
and took a sleeping child out of the bed.
وأخذ الطفل النائم من فراشه.
It's a very sad story.
لقد كانت قصة محزنة.
But even today,
لكن حتى اليوم،
that memory is still in people's minds.
مازلت تلك الذكرى في مخيلة الناس.
They can pinpoint the exact location
ويمكنهم تحديد الموقع بالضبط
where this all happened.
حيث حدث كل هذا.
And then, in the same year,
ثم، في نفس السنة،
we almost lost everything.
فقدنا كل شئ تقريباً.
And my father said, "Why don't you just go to school?"
وقد قال والدي، " لم لا تذهب إلى المدرسة؟"
And they sent me off to school, just to get busy somewhere there.
وقد أرسلوني إلى المدرسة، لمجرد أن أكون منشغلاً في مكان ما.
And the year I went to school,
وفي السنة التي ذهبت فيها إلى المدرسة،
my father actually got a job with a non-governmental organization
حصل والدي على وظيفة في منظمة غير حكومية
called IRDNC, Integrated Rural Development and Nature Conservation.
تسمى IRDNC-- التنمية الريفية المتكاملة والحفاظ على الطبيعة.
They actually spend a lot of time a year in the communities.
لقد كانوا يقضون الكثير من الوقت في السنة بين المجتمعات.
They were trusted by the local communities
كانت المجتمعات المحلية تثق بهم
like our leader, Joshua Kangombe.
مثل قادتنا، جوشوا كانغومبي.
Joshua Kangombe saw what was happening:
رأى جوشوا كانغومبي ما كان يحدث:
wildlife disappearing,
الحياة البرية تختفي،
poaching was skyrocketing,
الصيد الجائر كان مريعاً،
and the situation seemed very hopeless.
كانت الأوضاع تبدو ميؤوس منها.
Death and despair surrounded Joshua
أحاط الموت واليأس بجوشوا
and our entire communities.
وكل مجتمعاتنا.
But then, the people from IRDNC proposed to Joshua:
لكن عندئذ، أقترح موظفو IRDNC لجوشوا:
What if we pay people that you trust
ماذا لو قمنا بدفع المال لأناس تثق بهم
to look after wildlife?
ليقوموا برعاية الحياة البرية؟
Do you have anybody in your communities, or people,
هل لديك أي شخص في مجتمعك، أو أناس،
that know the bush very well
يعرفون الأدغال جيداً
and that know wildlife very well?
ويعرفون الحياة البرية جيداً ؟
The headman said: "Yes. Our poachers."
قال الزعيم " نعم، صيادونا."
"Eh? The poachers?"
"ماذا؟ الصيادون؟"
"Yes. Our poachers."
"نعم. صيادونا."
And that was my father.
وكان ذلك هو أبي.
My father has been a poacher for quite a long time.
لقد كان أبي صياداً لفترة طويلة جداً.
Instead of shooting poachers dead
بدلاً عن التعامل مع ديون الصيادين
like they were doing elsewhere in Africa,
مثلما يفعلون في أماكن أخرى في أفريقيا،
IRDNC has helped men reclaim their abilities
ساعدت IRDNC الرجال لإستعادة مقدراتهم
to manage their peoples
لتنظيم أهاليهم،
and their rights to own and manage wildlife.
وحقوقهم لإمتلاك وتنظيم الحياة البرية.
And thus, as people started feeling ownership over wildlife,
وعليه، لأن الناس قد بدأوا يشعرون بملكيتهم للحياة البرية،
wildlife numbers started coming back,
بدأت أعداد الحيوانات في الرجوع مجدداً،
and that's actually becoming a foundation for conservation in Namibia.
وأصبح ذلك في الواقع هو الأساس للحماية في ناميبيا.
With independence, the whole approach of community getting involved
مع حلول الإستقلال، كل مناهج إشراك المجتمع
was embraced by our new government.
تم تبنيها من قبل حكومتنا الجديدة.
Three things that actually help to build on this foundation:
في الواقع ثلاثة أشياء قد ساعدت في البناء على هذا الأساس:
The very first one is
أول شئ هو
honoring of tradition and being open to new ideas.
احترام التقاليد والإنفتاح على الأفكار الجديدة.
Here is our tradition:
ها هي تقاليدنا.
At every Himba village, there is a sacred fire.
في كل قرية لقبيلة الهيمبا، هناك نار مقدسة.
And at this sacred fire, the spirit of our ancestors
وعند هذه النار المقدسة، روح أسلافنا
speak through the headman
تتحدث عبر الزعيم
and advise us where to get water,
وترشدنا إلى مكان الماء،
where to get grazings,
أين نجد المرعى،
and where to go and hunt.
وإلى أين نذهب ونصيد.
And I think this is the best way of regulating ourselves
وأعتقد أن هذه هي أفضل طريقة لتنظيم أنفسنا
on the environment.
على البيئة.
And here are the new ideas.
وها هي الافكار الجديدة.
Transporting rhinos using helicopters
نقل وحيد القرن باستخدام طائرات الهلوكوبتر
I think is much easier
أعتقد أنه أسهل بكثير
than talking through a spirit that you can't see, isn't it?
من الحديث عن روح لا يمكنك رؤيتها، أليس كذلك؟
And these things we were taught by outsiders.
وهذه الأشياء التي تم تعليمنا إياها من قبل الأجانب.
We learned these things from outsiders.
لقد تعلمنا هذه الأشياء من الأجانب.
We needed new boundaries to describe our traditional lands;
لقد أحتجنا لحدود جديدة لتوضيح أراضينا التقليدية.
we needed to learn more things like GPS
لقد أحتجنا لتعلم أشياء أكثر مثل نظام تحديد المواقع(GPS)
just to see whether --
فقط لمعرفة إذا
can GPS really reflect the true reflection of the land
كان بإمكان ال (GPS) حقاً أن يعكس الإنعكاس الحقيقي للأرض
or is this just a thing made somewhere in the West?
أم أنه مجرد شئ تم صنعه في مكان ما في الغرب؟
And we then wanted to see whether we can match our
وعندها أردنا أن نرى سواء يمكننا مطابقة
ancestral maps with digital maps made somewhere in the world.
خرائط أسلافنا مع الخرائط الرقمية التي صُنعت في مكان ما في العالم.
And through this,
وعبر هذا،
we actually started realizing our dreams,
بدأنا في الواقع تحقيق أحلامنا
and we maintained honoring our traditions
وقد بقينا على احترام تقاليدنا
but we were still open to new ideas.
لكننا كنا ما نزال منفتحين على الأفكار الجديدة.
The second element is that we wanted to have a life,
الشئ الثاني هو أننا أردنا أن نحصل على حياة،
a better life where we can benefit through many things.
حياة أفضل حيث يمكننا الإستفادة من العديد من الأشياء.
Most poachers, like my father,
معظم الصيادين، مثل والدي،
were people from our own community.
كانوا أناساً من قلب مجتمعاتنا المحلية.
They were not people from outside.
لم يكونوا أناس من الخارج. "دُخلاء"
These were our own people.
هؤلاء كانوا أهلنا.
And sometimes, once they were caught,
وبعض الأحيان، بمجرد أن يتم القبض عليهم،
they were treated with respect, brought back into the communities
يُعاملون بكل إحترام، ويتم ارجاعهم إلى المجتمعات
and they were made part of the bigger dreams.
ويجعلونهم جزءاً من الحلم الأكبر.
The best one, like my father -- I'm not campaigning for my father --
أفضلهم، مثل والدي -- أنا لا أقوم بالترويج لوالدي --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
they were put in charge to stop others from poaching.
يوضعون في موقع المسئولية لإيقاف البقية عن الصيد الجائر.
And when this thing started going on,
وحينما بدأ هذا الشئ،
we started becoming one community,
بدأنا نصبح مجتمعاً موحداً.
renewing our connection to nature.
عرفنا تواصلنا مع الطبيعة.
And that was a very strong thing in Namibia.
وكان ذلك شئ عظيم جداً جداً في ناميبيا.
The last element that actually helped develop these things
والعنصر الأخير الذي ساعدنا في تطوير هذه الأشياء
was the partnerships.
كان الشراكة.
Our government has given legal status over our traditional lands.
قامت حكومتنا باعطاء شرعية على أراضينا التقليدية.
The other partners that we have got
بقية الشركاء الذين كانوا معنا
is business communities.
هم من مجتمع الأعمال.
Business communities helped bring Namibia onto the world map
ساعد مجتمع الأعمال في وضع ناميبيا على خارطة العالم
and they have also helped make wildlife
وقد ساعدوا أيضاً في جعل الحياة البرية
a very valuable land use like any other land uses
ذات قيمة كبيرة مثل أي إستخدامات أخرى للأرض
such as agriculture.
مثل الزراعة.
And most of my conservation colleagues today
ومعظم زملائي الذين يحافظون على البيئة اليوم
that you find in Namibia
الموجودين في ناميبيا
have been trained through the initiative,
قد تم تدريبهم عبر المبادرة،
through the involvement of World Wildlife Fund
عبر مشاركة الصندوق العالمي لدعم الحياة البرية
in the most up-to-date conservation practices.
في معظم ممارسات الحفاظ المواكبة للعصر.
They have also given funding for two decades
وقد قاموا أيضاً بتقديم تمويل لعقدين من الزمان
to this whole program.
لكل هذا البرنامج.
And so far, with the support of World Wildlife Fund,
وحتى الآن، و مع دعم صندوق الحياة البرية،
we've been able to scale up the very small programs
أستطعنا أن نوسع البرامج الصغيرة
to national programs today.
إلى برامج على المستوى الوطني اليوم.
Namibia ... or Sesfontein
ناميبيا...أو سيسفونتين
was no more an isolated village somewhere,
لم تكن سوى قرية معزولة في مكان ما،
hidden away in Namibia.
مخفية بعيداً في ناميبيا.
With these assets we are now part of the global village.
مع هذه الأصول نحن الآن جزء من القرية العالمية.
Thirty years have passed
مرّت ثلاثين سنة
since my father's first job as a community game guard.
منذ أن أستلم والدي عمله كحارس للعبة المجتمع.
It's very unfortunate that he passed away and he cannot see the success
ومن المؤسف أنه توفي ولا يمكنه رؤية النجاح
as I and my children see it today.
مثلما نراه أنا وأولادي اليوم.
When I finished school in 1995,
عندما أنتهيت من الدراسة عام ١٩٩٥،
there were only 20 lions in the entire Northwest -- in our area.
كان هناك فقط ٢٠ أسداً في كل الشمال الغربي -- في منطقتنا.
But today, there are more than 130 lions.
لكن اليوم، هناك أكثر من ١٣٠ أسداً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So please, if you go to Namibia,
لذا رجاءً، إذا ذهبتم إلى ناميبيا،
make sure that you stay in the tents.
تأكدوا من أن تقيموا في الخيام.
Don't walk out at night!
ولا تتمشوا في الليل!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The black rhino -- they were almost extinct in 1982.
وحيد القرن الأسود-- كان تقريباً قد إنقرض عام 1982.
But today, Kunene has the largest concentration of black rhino --
لكن اليوم، لدى كينيني أكبر تجمع لوحيد القرن الأسود --
free-roaming black rhinos -- in the world.
وحيد القرن الأسود الطليق -- في العالم.
This is outside the protected area.
هذا خارج المنطقة المحمية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The leopard -- they are now in big numbers
النمر -- إنه الآن بأعداد كبيرة
but they are now far away from our village,
لكنهم الآن بعيدون جداً من قريتنا،
because the natural plain has multiplied,
لأن السهول الطبيعية قد تضاعفت،
like zebras, springboks and everything.
مثل الحمار الوحشي، الغزلان وكل شئ.
They stay very much far away
إنهم يبقون بعيداً جداً
because this other thing has multiplied
لأن بقية الحيوانات قد تضاعفت
from less than a thousand to tens of thousands of animals.
من أقل من ألف إلى عشرات الألوف من الحيوانات.
What started as very small,
وما بدأ كشئ صغير جداً،
community rangers getting community involved,
حُراس المجتمع يحصلون على مشاركة المجتمع،
has now grown into something that we call conservancies.
قد نما الآن إلى شئ نسميه الحُماة البيئيين.
Conservancies are legally instituted institutions
الحُماة مؤسسات معترف بها قانونياً
by the government,
من قبل الحكومة،
and these are run by the communities themselves, for their benefit.
وهذه تُدار من قبل المجتمعات أنفسهم، لفائدتهم.
Today, we have got 60 conservancies
اليوم، لدينا ٦٠ حامي
that manage and protect over 13 million hectares
يديرون ويحمون ما يزيد على 13 مليون هكتار
of land in Namibia.
من الأرض في ناميبيا.
We have already reshaped conservation in the entire country.
لقد قمنا بالفعل باعادة رسم الحفاظ على البيئة في كل البلاد.
Nowhere else in the world
لا يوجد مكان آخر في العالم
has community-adopted conservation at this scale.
لديه مجتمع يتبنى الحفاظ على البيئة بهذا الحجم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In 2008, conservancy generated 5.7 million dollars.
عام ٢٠٠٨، قام الحُماة بجني ٥,٧ مليون دولار.
This is our new economy --
هذا هو إقتصادنا الجديد --
an economy based on the respect of our natural resources.
إقتصاد مبني على إحترام مواردنا الطبيعية.
And we are able to use this money for many things:
و نحن قادرون على إستخدام هذه الأموال لعدة أشياء.
Very importantly, we put it in education.
أهمها، أن نضعها في التعليم.
Secondly, we put it for infrastructure. Food.
ثانياً، نضعها من أجل البنية التحتية. الغذاء.
Very important as well -- we invest this money in AIDS and HIV education.
وبنفس الأهمية أيضاً -- نحن نستثمر هذه الأموال في التوعية بالإيدز و مرض نقص المناعة المكتسبة.
You know that Africa is being affected by these viruses.
كما تعلمون أن أفريقيا متأثرة بهذه الفيروسات.
And this is the good news from Africa
وهذه هي الأخبار السارة من أفريقيا
that we have to shout from the rooftops.
أنه ينبغي علينا الصراخ من سطوح منازلنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And now, what the world really needs
والآن، ما يحتاجه العالم حقاً
is for you to help me and our partners
هو أن تساعدوني وتساعدوا شركائنا
take some of what we have learned in Namibia
بأخذ بعض ما تعلمناه في ناميبيا
to other places with similar problems:
لأماكن أخرى لها مشاكل شبيهه:
places like Mongolia,
أماكن مثل منغوليا،
or even in your own backyards,
أو حتى في بلدكم الأم،
the Northern Great Plains,
السهول الشمالية العظمى،
where buffalo and other animals have suffered
حيث يعانى الجاموس وبقية الحيوانات
and many communities are in decline.
وتتدهور العديد من المجتمعات.
I like that one:
أحب ذلك الشئ.
Namibia serving as a model to Africa,
تقوم ناميبيا بتقديم النموذج لأفريقيا،
and Africa serving as a model to the United States.
وتقدم أفريقيا النموذج للولايات المتحدة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We were successful in Namibia
لقد كنا ناجحين في ناميبيا
because we dreamed of a future
لأننا حلمنا بالمستقبل
that was much more than just a healthy wildlife.
كان أكبر بكثير من مجرد حياة برية بصحة جيدة.
We knew conservation would fail
علمنا أن الحفاظ سيفشل
if it doesn't work to improve the lives of the local communities.
إذا لم يعمل لتحسين حياة المجتمعات المحلية.
So, come and talk to me about Namibia,
لذا، تعالوا وتحدثوا معي عن ناميبيا،
and better yet, come to Namibia
والأفضل من هذا، تعالوا لناميبيا
and see for yourself how we have done it.
لتروا بأنفسكم كيف أنجزنا ذلك.
And please, do visit our website
ورجاءً، قوموا بزيارة موقعنا الإلكتروني
to learn more and see how you can help CBNRM
لتعلموا أكثر ولتعرفوا كيف يمكنكم مساعدة CBNRM
in Africa and across the world.
في أفريقيا وعبر العالم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)